Okay, so in this video, we're going to be looking at the developer tools that are built
in to your browser.
Specifically, we're going to be looking at documentation for the Chrome Dev Tools, so Chrome
is by far the most popular browser.
I'm actually using Microsoft Edge, which is fundamentally the same as Chrome.
It's built with the same engine.
If you're using Firefox or Safari, the experience will be largely similar.
They will both have similar dev tools built into them.
Though the features might not be exactly the same, they will fundamentally do the same
things.
Okay, so Chrome Dev Tools.
So it's a set of tools to build directly into Chrome or whatever browser.
And it helps you edit pages on the fly, diagnose problems, and much, much more.
So how do we open the dev tools?
So if you right-click anywhere on the page, the very bottom, you can click Inspect.
This is a quick way.
There is also some keyboard shortcuts that you can use to open up your dev tools.
It will by default open into the Elements panel.
And that's the main panel that we're going to be focusing on for now.
We'll get more into other things within the dev tools as we get further into the course.
But basically, the things that we want to look at for now are viewing and changing the
DOM.
So the document object model.
So basically, that is our HTML, including our content, as well as the pages' styles.
So our CSS.
Eventually, we're going to look at it for optimizing our website as well.
But we'll get to that a little bit later on.
So the dev tools UI can seem a bit overwhelming.
There's a lot of tabs.
We're going to start out very slow, and again, just focus on one panel for now.
That is going to be very helpful for our HTML and CSS.
The other thing I want to point out is that it does contain a device mode, which is perfect
for testing our responsive design.
So it allows you to actually simulate a different device.
So in this case, it has an iPhone 6, and you can even flip it horizontal or vertical.
You can see that it is horizontal here.
So again, perfect for testing our mobile responsiveness on our websites.
You can even actually simulate that it's a little bit slower on a mobile device, which
it might be if it has, you know, mobile internet.
It might be slow in some cases.
And again, the main thing we're going to focus on is our elements panel.
And you can see at the top here that we have all of our HTML.
And at the bottom here, we have our styles.
And we also have our box model that we have mentioned before.
And you can see that there's a lot of different things that we can do here.
So you can click on each of these if you want to learn a little bit more, but we're
going to dive into most of this here.
So you can, again, view and change the DOM, view and change your CSS.
You can inspect and tweak your pages, edit your styles, edit the DOM.
There's lots of different things that you can do.
We'll dive into all this eventually as we get through the course.
And yeah, without further ado, let's actually, you know, see you at an action.
So I'm going to go back to my music player example here.
So this is a project that I had created previously in my previous course.
And I'm going to start by just right clicking and clicking inspect.
You see that this opens up my dev tools here.
And you'll notice we have our HTML here, and we have our styles down here, just like
we saw previously.
And the first thing I'm going to do is you can see that everything is collapsed.
I can actually right click on this line.
I can do a lot of different things.
I can add an attribute.
I could edit as HTML.
I could duplicate an element.
I could delete an element.
So it actually allows me to play around.
So let's say that I wanted to delete my body.
So if I do that, everything is gone.
So don't worry.
This is not permanent.
I can just refresh the page.
And everything will be exactly as it was.
This doesn't actually change your project.
It just changes what has actually loaded here on your machine.
But it doesn't actually change anything fundamentally about the project itself.
The other cool thing, if this is collapsed again, I can right click.
And there's a cool option here, expand recursively.
So what that does is it expands everything within the body.
So everything that was nested is now expanded.
So you can actually see my complete HTML here, which is very cool.
You can see that as I'm hovering over stuff, it is actually highlighting it within the
page here.
So that allows me to let's say I want to click on this.
And I want to check out the style for the duration.
You see that I actually have my specific styling here, which is very useful.
And you can see that I also have my box model here.
And as I hover over the content, you can see that it shows the content there.
There's no padding, border or margin.
So you can see those are all dashed out.
There's no number there.
But I can actually hover on it and it will actually show it, which is very cool.
So if I hover over something else, let's see, yeah.
So my progress container here, you can see that as I just hover over it, you see a lot
of orange.
And that's showing you that this is actually the margin.
And if I hover over it in real time, I can actually see the margin highlighted there, which
is very cool.
And I can see the content right there.
So it's 360 pixels wide and it's only four pixels tall, and then you can see the margin
outside.
Very cool.
So I can also scroll back up.
And again, I can see all of my styling here.
And from here, I can actually do something like change the color.
So I can click on this color input basically here.
And I can drag this and I can change the color of that and test out different colors.
I can actually even use the dropper tool to click somewhere.
Let's say I want this like blue color here.
And I can just click on that and it will actually change the color to that.
So that's very useful.
This eyedropper tool and you can see I have my hex code here.
I can copy and paste that as well.
So it's very great to be able to experiment with my colors within my dev tools.
I can take that even further if I want to change, let's say my border radius, or let's
say my width, that'll be more dramatic to see.
I can actually use my up and down arrow to actually change that again in real time and
see what that would look like.
So this is perfect for getting the perfect spacing for something.
You can actually do it in the dev tools.
Find out what the value is and then copy that value back into your code.
So again, you have to make sure you're copying it into your code if you want to have
it be a permanent change.
So that is very, very useful.
We also have, if you click up here, you'll notice we have a hover, an element state.
It's our hover pseudo class.
So if I click this, it will show any styling that is related to the hover.
In this case, there isn't any, I guess there is on my play button.
So I can actually use this also on the top left to select a specific element.
So you can just click on it on my main page and you'll see that it selects it here.
And if I click on that and I click the hover, you can see that it actually shows my hover
pseudo class here and it shows the styling here.
So I can change this to be 110, I'll change it 10%.
Okay, so you can see it got much darker.
So I changed how my hover works compared to how it was before, which is very cool.
And I'll just refresh the page to undo that.
And you'll see the cool thing, even when I refresh the page, everything goes back to
how it was, but it actually stays on the element that I had selected, which is very handy.
Okay, and other than that, we also even have something to work on our box shadows.
We have a box shadow inspector here.
So you can see that our shadow editor.
So you can see it has a little bit of a different symbol to our color picker, which we have
one here.
So if I click on this, you can see that I can actually change the values of my box shadow
in real time.
So if I turn this blur all the way down, you'll see that it just becomes a solid box.
I could change my offset to be more.
I can actually like drag it around like that, which is kind of cool.
So let's say I change it to that.
And then I can increase the blur back to actually make it look a little bit better.
And I could change the spread to make it larger.
So it's very cool to have a box shadow editor built into your dev tools because then you
can get the perfect box shadow just by adjusting these inputs here, which is very nice.
And I can do a similar thing with my RGB A. So see that this is a little bit different
instead of having a hex color.
It has my RGB, which is just black, is there all zero, but you can see I also have a slider
for my alpha value.
So I can actually slide this to change that alpha number.
And you'll see that that's obviously very dark.
And I can drag it all the way down if I want to make it a little bit of a lighter shadow.
This helps me kind of experiment with how much opacity I want on my box shadow.
So you can see that this is going to be very, very useful to test things kind of in real
time without having to do that trial and error.
It allows you to have a live preview within the browser of what it actually looks like.
And I think that that is something that is going to be super super useful for us, okay?
And moving on.
The next thing I wanted to show is the device mode here to the device emulation.
So again, this is all just in our elements panel.
That's all we're going to focus on for now.
And if I toggle this on, you'll see that it is simulating a Samsung Galaxy Ultra here.
And this is the screen size, it looks very similar, but you can see that it is a vertical
rectangle now.
And you can see that I can change it to throttle the internet performance just to check,
you know, how fast is my web project loading?
That's what that is for.
And I can also rotate it.
You'll see that it doesn't look perfect there, but it allows me to rotate to the horizontal
orientation.
So that again, is going to be perfect for our responsive design work that we're going
to do a little bit later in the course.
Okay, so that's kind of an overview of the developer tools.
It is very, very handy.
I will show one other thing.
So let's say that I delete my container here.
So I am also able to actually add.
So I can edit this as HTML, so you see that it just turns into HTML.
And I can actually add my own elements.
If I want to change things, I'll just show this as an example, oops.
And then I can click off of it and you'll see that, yep, we can actually modify this page
completely and add our own elements.
So that's another function of our div tools here.
Okay, very cool.
The very last thing I wanted to show as well is I'm going to refresh this one more time.
This is in the browser itself.
It's not quite the dev tools, but you'll notice when I clicked inspect above that.
We had an option to view page source.
So if I go ahead and click on that, it's actually going to load the HTML file, which
is very cool.
This is from my GitHub page.
And this is the complete HTML, and I'm also actually able to click on my style.css,
and I can actually see the CSS for the page.
And I can do the same thing for my script.js, so I can actually see the JavaScript.
So you can actually use these developer tools and this view page source on other websites.
Not everything is going to be maybe as transparent as this, and you might not be able to
see all the styles or the scripts.
But it's a great way to get ideas from HTML and CSS websites that you like, and maybe try
to see how some things are being done.
And if I go back to my source, I can even actually click on this JPEG, so it'll actually
load the raw image there, or I can click on the favicon, and it will load the raw favicon
there.
Yeah, we can also use view page source to kind of see under the hood of other websites.
Okay, very cool.
So that's a brief overview into the dev tools, and also view page source.
You'll see that there's a lot of power in the dev tools, and it's going to be very helpful
for our purposes of learning CSS and being able to tweak things in the browser is going
to be very, very helpful.
Alright, that's it for this one.
I'll see you next time.
Bye for now.